Guide to the Edmund Jennings Lee II Papers, 1797-1877 RL.11483
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edmund Jennings Lee II papers
1746-1963
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11483
9 Linear Feet
Correspondence, legal papers, and financial records concerning Edmund Jennings Lee’s law practice, estate settlements, and personal family matters. Subjects include Confederate refugees in Canada, the formation of West Virginia as a state, conditions of Virginia in 1865, and bridge and turnpike construction and management. Includes family writings and diary entries from Henrietta Bedinger Lee, Edmund Jennings Lee III, and Edwin Gray Lee. Also includes bills, receipts, and financial ledgers from Edmund Jennings Lee’s law practice.
Biographical / Historical
Edmund Jennings Lee II (1797-1877) was born in Alexandria, VA (then part of the District of Columbia). The eldest son of Edmund Jennings Lee and Sarah Lee, he graduated from Princeton College and studied law under his father. Lee was a first cousin of Robert E. Lee. His family was also related to the Rutherford, Lucas, Dandridge, Rust, Washington, Shepherd families. Lee practiced law first in Wheeling, WV and then in Shepherdstown, WV after marrying Henrietta Bedinger Lee. Despite prodding by his family, Lee declined on multiple occasions to enter a more public political life. He originally opposed Virginia’s secession from Union, but supported the state when it later did so. Lee continued to live in Shepherdstown for the rest of his life.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edmund Jennings Lee II Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1959, 1960, 1967, 1968, 1969, and 1972.
Collection Overview
The Edmund Jennings Lee II Papers have been divided into four series: Correspondence, Personal Files, Legal Papers, and Financial Records. The majority of materials concern Lee’s legal practice and business interests in Shepherdstown, WV. Materials include letters between Lee and his brothers, Charles Henry Lee, Richard Henry Lee, and Cassius Francis Lee; letters concerning family matters; legal briefs, documents, land surveys, bill, receipts, and financial ledgers from Lee’s legal practice; and miscellaneous family papers and writings, including diaries from Henrietta Bedinger Lee, Edmund Jennings Lee III, and Edwin Gray Lee.
Virginia -- Genealogy; West Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Probate law and practice -- Virginia
- Correspondence, 1797-1912 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence pertains mainly to Lee’s legal practice. Correspondents include his brothers, Charles Henry Lee, Richard Henry Lee, and Cassius Francis Lee, as well as other family members, including Lee’s son, Edwin Gray Lee. Other correspondents include Jubal A. Early and William Nelson Pendleton. Subjects include Confederate refugees in Canada, the formation of West Virginia as a state, conditions of Virginia in 1865, and bridge and turnpike construction and management. Also includes a letter from Rezin D. Shepherd from 1841 regarding the clock tower for Trinity Episcopal Church in Shepherdstown, WV. Letters from Edwin Gray Lee describe his service in the Confederate army and allude to his later work in the Confederate secret service in Virginia and Canada. Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Correspondence, 1797-1868; 28 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence among the brothers Edmund Jennings Lee II, Charles Henry Lee, Richard Henry Lee, and Cassius Francis Lee; primarily pertaining to Edmund Jennings Lee's legal practice. Also includes letters pertaining to family matters and service in the Confederate Army during the Civil War.
  - Correspondence, 1869-1912 and undated; 16 folders (Box 2)
    Correspondence among the brothers Edmund Jennings Lee II, Charles Henry Lee, Richard Henry Lee, Cassius Francis Lee and Edmund Jennings Lee's children; primarily pertaining to Edmund Jennings Lee's legal practice. Also includes letters pertaining to family matters.
- Personal Files, 1845-1963 and undated
  Personal Files includes miscellaneous writings from members of the Lee family; miscellaneous printed materials, including newspaper clippings and other ephemera; genealogy papers for the Parran and Lee families; and some photographs of buildings, landscapes, and individuals in Carlsbad, NM and Shepherdstown, WV. Also includes a volume with notes from a logic class taken by George Rust Bedinger at the University of Virginia in 1859. The volume includes some written correspondence from Shepherdstown, WV, poetry, and financial ledger sheets.
  The family writings include diary entries from Henrietta Bedinger Lee, Edmund Jennings Lee III, and Edwin Gray Lee. Henrietta’s diary focuses on religious themes based on several sermons. Her entries also include poems on her deceased children and a humorous dream about her husband’s first wife. Edmund’s diary entries are a few typescript copies of short entries of his daily activities in 1866. Edwin’s diary details his time in the Confederate army in the latter half of the Civil War, from 1864-1865. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - The Bells of Bedford, by Alexandra Lee Levin, 1850-1866 (Box 2)
    Manuscript draft, correspondence; includes letter from 1796
  - Diary of Edmund Jennings Lee III, 1866 (Box 2)
    Typescript copy
  - Diary of Edwin Gray Lee, 1865 (Box 2)
    Includes diary and enlarged photocopy
  - Diary of Henrietta Bedinger Lee, 1874-1877 (Box 2)
  - Genealogy papers for Parran family and Lee family, 1963 and undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous poetry and stories, 1867-1929 (Box 2)
    Includes typescript copies
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1845-1959 and undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    The Congressional Globe publications, business cards, flyers, pamphlets, legal forms
  - Newspaper clippings, 1875-1961 and undated (Box 2)
    The Register and New York Times; family events and legal matters in Shepherdstown, WV
  - Photographs, 1904 and undated (Box 2)
    Captioned photographs from Carlsbad, NM that includes photographs of buildings, landscapes, and a few local individuals. Also includes a few photographs from Shepherdstown, WV, including the view from Lee's home, Leeland, and a photograph of an elderly Henrietta Bedinger Lee
  - "Story of the Establishment of the Robert E. Lee Memorial Foundation", 1963 (Box 2)
    Speech by Mrs. Frank H. Griffin
  - Book of notes and correspondence, 1859-1875 (Box 6)
    Includes notes from a logic class taken by George Rust Bedinger at the University of Virginia in 1859. Also includes some written correspondence from Shepherdstown, WV, poetry, and financial ledger sheets
- Legal Papers, 1746-1875 and undated
  Legal Papers includes legal briefs, documents, ledger sheets, and land surveys from Lee’s legal practice, primarily in Shepherdstown, WV. Arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Bedinger family, 1770-1865 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, ledger sheets
  - Bradshaw Methodist Church, 1859-1860 (Box 3)
  - Boteler, Alexander R. and Dr. Henry Boteler, 1831-1854 and undated (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents
  - Briscoe, F. A. and L. J. vs. Quigley, 1837-1853 (Box 3)
  - Buckles, Daniel and Isaac, 1851-1859 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, land survey
  - Burns family, 1837-1853 (Box 3)
  - Cameron, Samuel, 1857-1858 (Box 3)
  - Catlett, William G., 1852 (Box 3)
  - Entler, Daniel and Joseph, 1843-1871 (Box 3)
  - Fairfax Estate, 1752-1833 (Box 3)
  - George Mason, 1767 and undated (Box 3)
    Legal arbitration between Peter Smith and James Jennings
  - Green, William, 1809 Sept., Nov. 20 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Oversize legal papers dividing the land owned by Green in Berkely County amongst his family.
  - Hamill, George and Giles C., undated (Box 3)
  - Harper, Robert, and Fairfax Estate, 1782-1833 and undated (Box 3)
  - Henkle family, 1844-1856 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, correspondence
  - Hollidat, John, 1849-1860 (Box 3)
  - Hessey family, 1853-1875 (Box 3)
  - Hodgson, Caroline guardianship, 1799-1852 (Box 3)
  - Johns Hopkins Bros. and Co., 1843-1846 and undated (Box 3)
  - Lane, Thomas C., 1833-1852 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, ledger sheets, indenture agreement
  - Leech, S. V. and others vs. J. L. Towner, 1853-1875 (Box 3)
  - McKewan, Michael, 1827 and undated (Box 3)
  - McVeigh brothers, 1853-1858 (Box 3)
  - Magowan, Abram, 1866 and undated (Box 3)
  - Mason, T. Washington, 1867-1875 (Box 3)
  - Moore, James V., 1860-1872 (Box 3)
  - Morgan County, WV, 1845 (Box 3)
    History of French Tract
  - Mutual Assurance Company, 1845-1868 (Box 3)
  - Orndorff, William, 1858-1873 (Box 3)
  - Peters Estate, 1843-1863 (Box 3)
  - Reynolds, Jacob W., 1853-1857 (Box 3)
  - Rutherford, Robert, 1773-1847 (Box 3)
  - Shepherd Family, 1834-1867 (Box 3)
  - Shepherdstown and Smithfield Turnpike Co., 1824 (Box 3)
    Ledger sheet
  - Showalter, William and Elizabeth, 1845 (Box 3)
  - Skrigg, William, 1839-1857 (Box 3)
  - Stephen, Adam, 1821-1839 (Box 3)
  - Strider, James guardianship, 1833-1862 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, ledger sheets, land surveys
  - Swearingen, Elizabeth, 1850 (Box 3)
    Legal document
  - Tarner Family, 1842-1869 (Box 3)
  - Towner, James L., 1855-1860 (Box 3)
  - Trinity Espicopal Church, 1818-1864 (Box 3)
    Shepherdstown, WV; legal briefs and documens, ledger sheets
  - Turberville case, 1746-1807 (Box 3)
    Legal briefs and documents, manuscript timeline
  - Virginia and Maryland Bridge Co. / Smithfield and Shepherdstown Turnpike, 1857-1875 (Box 3)
  - Washington, John Augustine, 1831-1873 (Box 3)
  - Washington, George vs. Michael Creasap land case, 1771-1825 (Box 3)
  - Wingerd, John, 1818-1831 (Box 3)
  - Yates, Francis, 1857-1858 (Box 3)
  - Claims and pensions, 1871 (Box 3)
  - Legal papers, lists, collections, 1856-1859 and undated (Box 3)
  - Lists, collections, dockets, 1851-1868 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous land plots and deeds, 1847 and undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1801-1873 and undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Notebook, 1799-1830 (Box 5)
    Handwritten notes on legal terms and procedures
- Financial Records, 1814-1879 and undated
  Financial Records is comprised of bills, receipts, and financial ledgers from Lee’s legal practice and business interests, primarily in Shepherdstown, WV. Also included are financial ledgers from the Virginia-Maryland Bridge Company and the Shepherdstown and Winchester Turnpike Company. Bills and receipts are arranged chronologically by year. Ledgers are listed individually.
  - Bills and receipts, 1814-1879 and undated; 27 folders (Box 4)
    Primarily from Leeland, near Shepherdstown, WV
  - Mutual Assurance Society of Richmond, 1852-1859 (Box 4)
    Insurance documents
  - Docket ledger, 1841-1848 (Box 5)
    Financial records, debts, and brief case notes
  - Ledger, 1839-1858 (Box 5)
    Shepherdstown, WV; financial records arranged both chronologically by year and by name of individual
  - Ledger, Virginia-Maryland Bridge Co., 1849-1851 (Box 6)
    Financial records arranged alphabetically by last name
  - Ledger, Shepherdstown and Winchester Turnpike Road Co., 1818-1848 (Box 6)
    Financial records arranged chronologically by year
  - Ledger, 1835-1838 (Box 5)
  - Ledger, 1843-1853 (Box 5)
  - Daybook, 1848-1876 (Box 8)
    "Leeland," near Shepherdstown, WV; financial records arranged both chronologically by year and by name of individual. Principally a toll book.
  - Ledger, 1856-1875 (Box 9)
  - Ledger, 1841-1860 (Box 6)